TROLL
There are no major changes.
大きな変更はない。
You will be compensated
with five pounds of gold.
報酬は金5ポンド。
I will only pay you in exchange for his dead body.
奴の死体と引き換えでなければ払わんぞ。
You can do whatever you want with their ship
and their cargo.
奴の船と積み荷はお前たちの好きにしていい
Kill Thors.
トールズを殺せ
-Go ahead, boy.
-My turn next.
おら！いったるぜ坊主！
次オレ！次オレ！
Thors?
トールズね…
The Troll of Jom.
“ヨームの戦鬼”
I've heard of him before.
聞いたことありますよ。
Are you sure it's okay if I kill him?
He's a hero to you guys.
いいんですか？殺しちゃって。あんた方にとっちゃ英雄でしょ？
If he were a hero, I wouldn't have told you to kill him.
英雄なら殺せなどと言わん。
He broke military law.
奴は重大な軍規違反者だ。
He deserted during battle.
敵前逃亡罪。
Orders to have him executed were issued
15 years ago.
処刑の命令は15年も前に下されている
I know you have strict laws,
but it's been 15 years.
あんた方が規則にうるさいのは知ってっけど。
いやはや15年ですか…
Thanks.
ご苦労さまで
No, don't get the wrong idea.
あーいやいや。
As long as I receive fair payment,
こちらは応分の金がもらえりゃもうハイ。
I'll do any job.
どんな仕事でも
But you know, master...
ただねだんな…
If you're going to execute one of your own,
one of your own should kill him.
身内の処刑なら身内で殺るのが普通かな
って思いまして…
You went to Iceland, right?
行ったんでしょ。アイスランドまで。
Why didn't you kill him there?
どうしてその場で殺さなかったんですか？
This Christian monk is dead.
あっ、このキリスト坊主死んでるぞ
It's none of your business.
貴様らの知ったことではないな。
You shouldn't ask questions.
It's for your own good.
それ以上つべこべ聞かん方が身のためだ
Well, all right.
まぁいいでしょ。
Five extra pounds of gold, paid in advance.
前金でさらに金5ポンド。
Then I'll accept your job.
それで引き受けましょ
You think you have the upper hand on me.
You must be confident in yourself.
オレにそんなナメた口を利くとは大きく出たな
Oops, sorry.
ありゃ～すんませーん！！
It slipped. Are you okay?
すっぽ抜けちゃって！！おケガないすかぁ？
Hey. Be careful.
オイオイ！気をつけろよ！
You guys almost hit me.
オレに当たるトコだったぞ君たちぃ～
You klutz.
ドヘタクソーッ！
You drank too much.
飲みすぎだぜビョルン！
Five extra pounds of gold, paid in advance.
前金で金5ポンド追加…
You accept?
ってことでよろしいかな？
All right.
いいだろう
Excellent, master.
You're a great man. See you later.
さっすがだんな！男前だなぁ。では後ほど
And by the way...
ああそーそー。
What kind of a warrior is Thors?
トールズってのはどんな戦士なんすかね？
What does he look like? How does he fight?
見た目とか戦い方とか…
Thors is no longer a warrior.
トールズは…すでに戦士ではない
Okay. That's enough drinking.
ハイハイ！酒盛り終わり！
It's time to work, you bastards.
お仕事の時間だぜ野郎ども！
Bjorn. Nice spear throw.
ビョルン。いい槍だったぜ
No sweat.
朝メシ前よ
Even Floki was in shock.
さすがのフローキのだんなもめんくらってたよ
I wish I could have seen it myself.
そいつァ見たかったな
It seems he's not a man of empty words.
口だけではないようだな
The time has come for me,
Ari, son of Geitr, to become a man.
このゲイテルの子アーレ。オトコになる時が来たんだ。
I know. Don't say a word.
It will not be an easy journey.
わかってる何も言うな。もちろん楽な旅ではないだろう
There's no guarantee that I won't be injured in battle.
さすがのオレも戦場で手傷を負わないとゆー保証はない。
But I shall return.
だが必ず帰ってくる！
I'll return with a necklace
I seized from England as a gift to you.
その時は君にイングランドでぶんどってきた首飾りをプレゼントするよ！
-And then will you...?
-Hey, I'm still sleepy.
そしたらオレと…その…
ねぇアタシまだ眠いんだけど…
Ma-- Marry...
けっ…けっけっ…けっこ…
Ari.
アーレー！！
You forgot your lunch.
おーべーんーとー！お弁当忘れてる！
Mom?
母ちゃん！
Why are you so careless?
あんたはもーどうしてそうそそっかしいのかねぇ。
Make sure you share the salted herring
with everyone else.
ニシンの塩漬けはみんなにも分けなさいね。
-I stuffed it full.
-Mom. Wait over there.
たくさん入れといたから…
あっち行ってろよ母ちゃん！！
How can you say that to your own mother?
あんた！母親に向かって！
-When I return...
-What's wrong...?
続きは帰ってから話すよ。
I'll finish what I was saying.
Wait for me, Ylva.
待っててなユルヴァ！
They're departing today.
ああ…今日出港かー。
I hope they don't die.
死ななきゃいいけどねー…
Ylva.
ユルヴァ！
Do you have a moment?
ちょ…ちょっといいかな…
Wait. I'm first.
待てよ！オレが先だ！
Hey. Ylva.
お～いユルヴァ～！
Can you try somewhere else?
…ヨソあたってくれる？
Make sure you bathe on Saturday, my boy.
土曜日にはちゃんと体を洗うのよ、ぼうや
I know, Mom.
わかってるよママ
I swear on my father's ax.
父祖の斧にかけて！
I shall bring back a barrel full of gold coins.
大ダルいっぱいの金貨を持ち帰るぜ！
They're so excited.
ハリキっとるなぁ若衆たち
But there's only five of them in total.
That's not enough.
しかし全部で5人とはちと少なすぎやせんかの？
Thors says that five is enough.
トールズが5人でいいとゆうとるんじゃ
Well, if that's what he says.
まあ奴がそう言うんじゃしかたないな
But that's barely enough
for sailing two ships.
しかしのぉ。やっとこ船を動かせるギリギリの人数じゃ
It's Thors we're talking about.
I'm sure he has a reason.
そこはホレ。あの人のことだ。何か考えがあるんだろ
Hey. What were you talking about with Ylva just now?
おいこら。てめぇさっきユルヴァと何話してた？
Shut up, you jackass. You stay away from her.
黙れタコ。てめぇこそあの娘にかまうんじゃねーぞ
Watch your back on the battlefield.
戦場じゃ背中に気をつけろよ
Don't underestimate me.
I was going to say the same thing to you.
なめんな。そりゃこっちのセリフだぜ
-Ari.
-What?
アーレ！
あぁ！？
Be careful.
気をつけてね
You didn't finish.
済んでねえぞゴラァ！
What did you say?
んだとオルァ！
This way.
先行くんじゃねぇ！
Miss.
おじょうちゃん
Are you worried about Ari?
アーレが心配かね？
Want me to tell you a secret?
ならイイコト教えてあげようか
What? They're not going to battle?
え！？戦場に行かないの！？
It's a secret.
ナイショナイショ。
We're going to stop by Norway
on our way to Jomsborg.
ヨムスボルグに行く途中、一度ノルウェーに寄る
Thors plans to leave the young men behind there.
トールズの奴、若造どもをそこへおいてけぼりにするつもりだ
Thors is going to get some help
from some sailors in Norway
そこから先、トールズはノルウェーの船乗りの助けを借りて
to make it to Jomsborg.
ムスボルグへ向かう
I'm friends with the previous King of Norway.
ワシャ先代のノルウェー王とは友達でな。
I have a lot of influence there.
ノルウェーじゃ顔が利く
As soon as I'm done with my business,
んでワシの商売が済みしだい、
I'll bring the young men back here.
若造どもを連れて帰る
Five men is the most I can bring back
on my run-down ship.
5人ちゅーのはワシのボロ船で連れ帰れる限度にすぎん。
He won't bring anyone to the battlefield.
あいつは誰ひとり戦場へ連れていかんよ。
That's the kind of person that Thors is.
トールズとはそういう男だ
Thorfinn.
トルフィーン！！
Hey. Where are you?
おォい！！どこだぁ！？
Thorfinn.
トルフィーン！！
Excuse me, Leif...
あの…レイフさん…
Does that mean Thors is going
to the battlefield alone?
それじゃ…トールズさんは独りで戦場へ行くの？
Ready to row?
櫂走準備ーー！
Yeah.
おうっ！！
What's wrong with his oar?
なに…？あのオール…
I can't believe Thorfinn isn't seeing Father off.
トルフィンのヤツ～！父上のお見送りもしないなんて！
I bet he's still angry he got scolded yesterday.
昨日怒られたの根に持ってんだわアイツ
-Helga.
-Yes?
ヘルガ
はい
Tell Thorfinn...
トルフィンに伝えてくれ
Well...
その…
What I mean is...
…つまり…
Yes. I'll tell him.
はい。伝えておきます
I'm counting on you.
頼む
All right. Depart.
おーし！出港ォーー！！
He's so strong.
なっ…なんちゅーチカラ…
Idiot. Don't stop rowing.
バカ！手を休めんな！
Row. Row.
漕げ漕げ！！
You can do it.
頑張れよ！頑張ってこいよ～！
Bring home some souvenirs.
See you.
Raise the sail.
帆を張れーっ！！
My hands are peeling.
あぁ…手の皮がベロベロだぁ…
My butt. My butt.
尻が…尻が…
Hey. Hang in there.
おいしっかりしろ！
Ari. Take the rudder.
アーレ。舵をとれ。
Mord and Magni, adjust the mainsheet.
Hakon and Grim, take the jib sheet.
モードとマグニは帆裾索の調節。ハーコンとグリムは横桁索だ
Are you tired?
疲れたか？
No. It's nothing.
なっ…なんの…
Don't worry.
We don't have to row any more for a while.
安心しろ。もう当分は漕がなくていい。
We're riding the current now.
The ship will move on its own.
潮流に乗ったから、あとは勝手に進むよ
Does that mean we can't turn back anymore, Father?
それって、もう引き返せないってこと？父上！
Yeah, that's right.
まぁそうだな…
"Father"?
父上！？
Thor--?
ト…
Thorfinn? You...
トルフィンお前…！？
You can tell me later.
あとにして！！
I made it...
セーフ…
You naughty--
こっのっ…イタズラ…
Father.
父上！！
It's the ocean.
海だ！！
This job is suspicious.
しかしキナ臭いなこのヤマ
Why?
なんで？
Floki is hiding too many secrets.
フローキのだんなさ。どうも隠し事が多すぎる。
He's lying about the execution order for Thors.
トールズ処刑の命令ってのはウソだな、
I'm almost certain of it.
ほぼ確実に
Then why...?
じゃあ…
It's an assassination.
暗殺さ。
Maybe it's a personal grudge or something.
But I'm sure he cooked this up all on his own.
私怨かなんか知らんが多分すべて奴の独断だ
Who cares?
それがどうしたよ。
It doesn't change the fact
that you'll get paid for killing him.
殺して金もらうことにかわりはねぇだろ？
Why do you think he didn't use one of his own men?
奴が自分の部下を使わないのはなぜだと思う？
Because that'd be going against orders.
He'd get his hands dirty.
命令違反のヨゴレ仕事だからじゃねーの？
Well, that could be true.
まぁな。それもあるだろうが…
What if he's afraid of a loss?
損害を恐れているんだとしたら？
A loss so large that he won't
be able to explain it to his boss.
それも首領にいいわけがきかねぇほどの大損害だ
An entire Jomsvikings unit?
ヨーム戦士団一個小隊がか？
Just to get one washed-up soldier? That's crazy.
中古戦士ひとりに？んなバカな…
Hey. Come down from there, kid.
コラ！！おりてこい悪ガキ！
I want to get a look at this guy.
ツラ拝んでみたくなったぜ
"The Troll of Jom."
“ヨームの戦鬼”…
I hope he's a fun guy.
少しャァ楽しめる男だとうれしいね
I can't even see the stars. I can't see anything.
星も見えないなーんにも見えない。
Which way are we heading?
一体どっちに向かってんだ？
Thors.
トールズ！
The wind changed a bit. Slightly to the right.
風が少し変わった！チョイ右だ。
I'll lead. Follow me.
先行する。ついてきてくれ
Got it.
わかった
Amazing.
スゲェなぁ…
How can Leif sail through the sea like this
without getting lost?
レイフさんはどーしてこんな海を迷わず進めるんだ…？
Ari.
アーレ。
Don't stare into the sea at night.
あまり夜の海を見つめるな。
It'll pull you in.
引きずり込まれるぞ
Hey, Thors.
ねぇトールズさん。
What is it like on the battlefield?
戦場ってどんな所なんすか？
I heard you fought in a lot of battles.
トールズさんはあちこちで戦ってきたんでしょ？
Tell us some stories.
手柄話聞かせて下さいよ。
I want to cut off some general's head,
オレも一発大将首とって
so I can become a real man too.
オトコになりてぇんだ！
I see.
なるほどな…
My daughter likes strong men.
確かにウチの娘は強い男が好みだ。
You have a tough job ahead.
大変だなお前も
Well, what can I say?
えっ…イヤまー…まいったな。
You can tell?
お見通しですか
Are you in love with Ylva, Ari?
ユルヴァが好きか？アーレ
Yeah, I like her. She's cute.
いやー好みっすねー！かわいっす！
She was born while I was still
in the Jomsvikings army.
あいつはオレがまだヨームの軍団にいた頃に生まれた子でな。
She was my first child.
オレの初めての子なんだ
You're so loud.
うるせぇな。
Do all babies cry so much?
赤ん坊ってのはみんなこんなに泣くもんなのか？
-Thors. Don't hold her like that.
-Her neck. Support her neck.
トールズ様、そのような持ち方をされては…
首！首を支えて
Give me a boy next, Helga.
次は男を産めヘルガ。
The leader wants a boy.
首領は男の子をお望みだ
My wife Helga is the daughter of the leader
of the army.
妻のヘルガは軍団の首領の娘なんだ。
It was a difficult birth. She looked pale.
難産のあとで病人のような顔色だった
Thors.
トールズ。
Give her a name.
名前をつけてあげて…
Name her as you see fit.
適当につけておけ。
I'm busy.
オレは忙しい。
We're about to go on a campaign to Norway.
これからノルウェーへ遠征だ
Thors, the ship will soon depart.
トールズ殿。船が出ます
Okay. I'm coming.
おう。今行く
Thors.
トールズ！
Give this child a name.
この子に名前を
I've been with her for 15 years,
その後15年一緒にいるが、
but that's the only time
ヘルガが怒ったのは
I've ever seen Helga mad.
その時だけだ
Ylva was my mother's name.
ユルヴァという名はオレの母の名だ。
It came to me all of a sudden.
とっさに浮かんだ。
Now that I think about it, that's when it started.
今思えば…あの時からだ。
That's when I started to get scared of battle.
オレはすっかり戦場が怖くなっちまった。
That's why I ran away.
だから逃げたんだ。
I bet my old war buddies would curse me
if they knew.
昔を知る戦友たちはオレを罵るだろうな
Hey. I can see the Faroe Islands.
おぉい！フェローが見えたぞー！
Father. Father.
父上！父上ーっ！！
Are we in England? Did we arrive in England?
ねぇ、ここイングランド！？イングランドに着いたの！？
No. Wrong answer.
ぜんぜん不正解～
These are the Faroe Islands.
ここはフェロー諸島。
They're in the middle, between Iceland and Norway.
アイスランドとノルウェーの真ん中だ。
Our journey will be easier if we rest here for a bit.
ここで一休みすると旅が楽になる
There's a village beyond this cove.
この先の入り江に村があるんだ。
Let's get some water there.
And we can trade too.
そこで飲み水を補給しよう。商売もできるぜ
Are you planning to come along,
all the way to England?
つーかお前、イングランドまでついてくるつもりか？
Yeah.
うん！
Get ready to row.
櫂走準備ーッ！
Come on, hang in there.
そーら頑張れ！
I wish we didn't have to do this.
これさえ…なけりゃなー。
My butt hurts.
ケツいて～！
What's wrong, Leif?
どうした？レイフさん
Something's wrong.
おかしい
What's wrong?
何がだ？
I wonder what's wrong.
さて何がだろう…
Something feels different
from the last time I was here.
だが前に来た時とは何かが…
I see. It's the number of houses.
そうか…家の数だ。
The number of houses decreased.
家の数が減っている
Let's turn back, Leif. I have a bad feeling about this.
引き返そう、レイフさん。よくない気配がする。
The terrain's bad too.
地形も悪い
What? Are you serious?
えーっ！？マジですかぁ？
Hey. They're going backwards.
オイ！あいつら逆走してるぞ！
Did they notice us?
チッ！気づいたか
They're good.
へぇ、やるのぉ
They're very careful. They might be strong.
慎重だな。手ごわいかもしれねえぞ
They're too close, but it can't be helped.
近すぎるがしかたねぇ。
I don't care if the ships get damaged. Do it.
多少船が傷ついてもかまわん！やれ！
Our exit...
な…入り江の出口が…
Take that.
どうだ！？
Great. They're caught like rats in a trap.
よーし上々。奴らフクロのネズミだ
Thors. Everyone. Are you okay?
トールズ！！みんな！！大丈夫か！？
Is everyone okay?
全員無事か！？
-Yes.
-We're okay.
は、はい…！
なんとか…
They will fire arrows.
Cover your head with your shield.
矢がくるぞ！盾で頭を隠せ！
Leif. How's the damage over there?
レイフさん、そっちの被害は！？
We're okay. The ship is fine and everyone is okay.
大丈夫だ！船も人も何ともない！
They're coming.
くるぞ。
Whoever's behind this trap
is in the back of the cove.
このワナの本命は…入り江の奥だ！！
The back?
奥？
Pirates?
海賊…！
These pillars are from a house.
こりゃア家の柱か…
We're completely blocked.
なんてこった完全に塞がれてる
They got us.
やられた…
Maybe they'll spare our lives if we surrender.
こっ…降参すれば助かるんじゃないか？
How do you know?
わかんねーよ！
They won't spare our lives.
助かるわきゃねーだろ！
If they catch us, they'll sell us at the slave market.
Get ready.
捕まりゃ奴隷市場で売られるだけだ！腹をくくれ！
This is nothing.
どっどっどっ…どおってことねーよ！
There's only two ships.
たった2隻だ…
Stop, Ari.
よせアーレ。
They're experienced.
奴らは手練れだ。
They're not just some farmers working as pirates
in the summer for some extra cash.
農民が夏場の出稼ぎでやってる海賊とはワケが違う。
You're no match for them.
お前のかなう相手じゃない
Father...
ちっ…父上…
Thors...
トールズさん？
Thorfinn.
トルフィン。
Use it only to protect yourself. Understand?
身を守るためだけに使え いいな！
Only when you really need it.
イザという時だけだぞ
Are you going to kill them?
You are going to kill them.
やややっ、やっぱやるんすか！？殺るんすね！！
All right. I'm going to kill them.
よよよ～し！殺るぞ～ッ！！
Stop saying "kill" so lightly.
簡単に“殺る”なんて言うな
Bjorn. That mushroom...
ビョルン！あんたそのキノコ…
One, two, three...
ひー…ふー…みー…
11, 12... And one kid?
11…12…と？ガキが1匹
What? Is that all?
なんでぇ。それっぽっちかよ。
Hey. Askeladd.
うぉい！アシェラッドー！
Is it okay if I take care of them?
あれオレに任せてくんねーか？
It wouldn't be fun if all of us went after them at once.
あれっぱかしに全員でかかっちゃ面白くねえ。
I'll go see
how good the Troll of Jom really is.
“ヨームの戦鬼”ってぇのがどんなもんかオレが試してやるよ
Okay. They look like they want a fight too.
いいだろう。向こうもその気みたいだしね
What?
あ？
-What?
-You bastard.
な…！
こっ…コイツ！
What's wrong with you?
なっ…なんだテメェ！！
Where did you come from?
どっから降ってきやがった！！
Brother.
兄貴！
He's good.
やるぜこいつ！
Take this.
おりゃあぁっ！！
You're good...
やるねぇ…
Troll of Jom.
“ヨームの戦鬼”